<article><preamble>On_the_Morality_of_Artificial_Intelligence.pdf</preamble>
<titre>arXiv:1912.11945v1  [cs.CY]  26 Dec 2019</titre>
<auteurs></auteurs>
<abstract>4
ConclusionTechnology in general, and ML more speciﬁcally, carries a great potential for change and disruption. While
neither of these is guaranteed to make the world a better place, this potential can most deﬁnitely be used
to have a positive impact on the world. In the present article, we have illustrated some inspiring projects
that aim to make the world a better place and by using the powerful techniques and approaches that ML has
brought forward. We believe that as ML researchers and practitioners, we have the responsibility to leverage
our (super)powers to contribute to these efforts. This can be done by connecting with established actors from
industry and policy or experts from other relevant disciplines, by learning from their past experiences, and
by working together to propose innovative solutions to major problems, deployed in places where they will
have a positive impact.
We live in a world with many global and local challenges and issues that are in constant evolution, and
it is easy to be overwhelmed by this ﬂux of information and focus on a small sandbox in which we feel
safe and in control, in order to develop and study the aspects of ML that interest us most. But it is naive
9</abstract>
<introduction>2
Ethics and AI - Existing InitiativesIn recent years, there have been numerous initiatives which have taken one of two major approaches to
fostering the ethical practice of AI: (1) Proposing principles guiding the socially responsible development
of AI or (2) Raising concerns about the social impact of AI. We will describe both approaches in the current
section, as well as giving examples of notable initiatives and projects which have adopted either of the
approaches.11For a more complete overview of different global ML ethics initiatives, see a recent review in Jobin et al. [2019]22.1
Deﬁning Principles for Practicing AI ResponsiblyThe topic of ethical research and practice in technology has been gaining momentum in different corners of
the computing community in recent years, and the various initiatives that have been proposed are indicative
of the interest and the concern that many members share. For instance, in the United States, the Association
for Computing Machinery (ACM) has proposed a Code of Ethics and Professional Conduct, to be followed
by all members of the association and to guide them in their usage of computer science [Gotterbarn et al.,
2018]. A similar initiative was undertaken by the Royal Statistical Society (RSS) in the United Kingdom,
which has created a practical guide for practitioners regarding the ethical use of mathematics [RSS, 2019].
In the present section, we will address the two most relevant and extensive initiatives to establish ethical
guidelines for AI research and practice: the Montreal Declaration for Responsible Development of AI and
the IEEE report for Ethically Aligned Design.</introduction>
<corps>While changes in our climate can be abstract, quantiﬁed in degrees of warming or tons of CO2, climate
change will also have very concrete impacts on society, for instance by decreasing crop yield, increasing
the frequency of extreme weather events such as hurricanes and storms, and impacting biodiversity. There
are a myriad of ways in which ML can help face these, whether it be by analyzing real-time images and
recordings of ecosystems to detect species [Duhart et al., 2018] and deforestation [McDowell et al., 2015],
improving disaster preparation and response by generating real-time maps from satellite imagery [Voigt
et al., 2007] and even setting an optimal price on carbon to accelerate the transition to a low-carbon energy
economy [Wei et al., 2018]. Finally, while we are far from being able to predict the exact impact that
increasing the carbon tax will have on the different levels of society and industry (i.e. federal and regional
governments, local and international companies, and individuals), this is a worthwhile area of research and
exploration, with potentially huge consequences in helping political leaders make more informed choices
in addressing the climate crisis. It is therefore useful to continue gathering data and building trust between
members of the political ecosystem and ML practitioners to learn from each other and to facilitate the
deployment of technological solutions in setting government policies.
On an individual level, there are many reasons why individuals cannot, or will not, act on climate change,
either common misconceptions regarding the fact that individuals cannot make meaningful impact on a
global problem, or cognitive biases that increase an individual’s psychological distance to climate change.
In the ﬁrst case, ML-infused tools to estimate the carbon footprint of individuals and households [Jones and
Kammen, 2011] and to model individual behavior with regards to sustainable lifestyle choices and technolo-
gies [Carr-Cornish et al., 2011] can be very useful if they are sufﬁciently accurate and deployed on a large
scale. Finally, minimizing psychological distance to the future effects of climate change is a promising way
to reduce cognitive bias – in this regard, it is possible to use images generated using Generative Adversarial
Networks (GANs) which represent the impacts of extreme events on locations that have personal value to
the viewer [Schmidt et al., 2019]. A crucial part of developing ML tools for individuals is, once again,
working with multidisciplinary experts in psychology, scientiﬁc communication, and user design to ensure
that the tools created reach the largest possible audience and maximize their positive impact.</corps>
<discussion>N/A</discussion>
<conclusion>Technology in general, and ML more speciﬁcally, carries a great potential for change and disruption. While
neither of these is guaranteed to make the world a better place, this potential can most deﬁnitely be used
to have a positive impact on the world. In the present article, we have illustrated some inspiring projects
that aim to make the world a better place and by using the powerful techniques and approaches that ML has
brought forward. We believe that as ML researchers and practitioners, we have the responsibility to leverage
our (super)powers to contribute to these efforts. This can be done by connecting with established actors from
industry and policy or experts from other relevant disciplines, by learning from their past experiences, and
by working together to propose innovative solutions to major problems, deployed in places where they will
have a positive impact.
We live in a world with many global and local challenges and issues that are in constant evolution, and
it is easy to be overwhelmed by this ﬂux of information and focus on a small sandbox in which we feel
safe and in control, in order to develop and study the aspects of ML that interest us most. But it is naive
9</conclusion>
<biblio>Robert G Abbott. Automated expert modeling for automated student evaluation. InInternational Confer-
ence on Intelligent Tutoring Systems, pages 1–10. Springer, 2006.
M Allen, P Antwi-Agyei, F Aragon-Durand, M Babiker, P Bertoldi, M Bind, S Brown, M Buckeridge,
I Camilloni, A Cartwright, et al. Technical summary: Global warming of 1.5c. an ipcc special report
on the impacts of global warming of 1.5c above pre-industrial levels and related global greenhouse gas
emission pathways, in the context of strengthening the global response to the threat of climate change,
sustainable development, and efforts to eradicate poverty, 2019.
Julia
Angwin,
Jeff
Larson,
Surya
Mattu,
and
Lauren
Kirchner.
Machine
bias,
propub-
lica.https://www.propublica.org/article/machine-bias-risk-assessments-
in-criminal-sentencing, 2016. Accessed: 2019-11-25.
Filippo Arcadu, Fethallah Benmansour, Andreas Maunz, Jeff Willis, Zdenka Haskova, and Marco Prunotto.
Deep learning algorithm predicts diabetic retinopathy progression in individual patients.NPJ digital
medicine, 2(1):1–9, 2019.
UN General Assembly. Universal declaration of human rights.UN General Assembly, 302(2), 1948.
Tolga Bolukbasi, Kai-Wei Chang, James Y Zou, Venkatesh Saligrama, and Adam T Kalai. Man is to
computer programmer as woman is to homemaker? debiasing word embeddings. InAdvances in neural
information processing systems, pages 4349–4357, 2016.
Joy Buolamwini and Timnit Gebru. Gender shades: Intersectional accuracy disparities in commercial gen-
der classiﬁcation. InConference on fairness, accountability and transparency, pages 77–91, 2018.
Simone Carr-Cornish, Peta Ashworth, John Gardner, and Stephen J Fraser.
Exploring the orientations
which characterise the likely public acceptance of low emission energy technologies.Climatic change,
107(3-4):549–565, 2011.
Devendra Singh Chaplot, Eunhee Rhim, and Jihie Kim. Predicting student attrition in moocs using senti-
ment analysis and neural networks. InAIED Workshops, volume 53, pages 54–57, 2015.
Cristina Conati, Kaska Porayska-Pomsta, and Manolis Mavrikis. Ai in education needs interpretable ma-
chine learning: Lessons from open learner modelling.arXiv preprint arXiv:1807.00154, 2018.
Jeffrey Dastin. Amazon scraps secret ai recruiting tool that showed bias against women, reuters business
news.https://www.reuters.com/article/us-amazon-com-jobs-automation-
insight/amazon-scraps-secret-ai-recruiting-tool-that-showed-bias-
against-women-idUSKCN1MK08G, 2018. Accessed: 2019-11-25.
Jia Deng, Wei Dong, Richard Socher, Li-Jia Li, Kai Li, and Li Fei-Fei. Imagenet: A large-scale hierarchical
image database. In2009 IEEE conference on computer vision and pattern recognition, pages 248–255.
Ieee, 2009.
Clement Duhart, Gershon Dublon, Brian Mayton, and Joseph Paradiso.
Deep learning locally trained
wildlife sensing in real acoustic wetland environment. InInternational Symposium on Signal Processing
and Intelligent Recognition Systems, pages 3–14. Springer, 2018.
10Ashish Dutt, Maizatul Akmar Ismail, and Tutut Herawan. A systematic review on educational data mining.IEEE Access, 5:15991–16005, 2017.
Marzyeh Ghassemi, Tristan Naumann, Peter Schulam, Andrew L Beam, and Rajesh Ranganath. Opportu-
nities in machine learning for healthcare.arXiv preprint arXiv:1806.00388, 2018.
Jeffrey Alan Golden. Deep learning algorithms for detection of lymph node metastases from breast cancer:
helping artiﬁcial intelligence be seen.Jama, 318(22):2184–2186, 2017.
Ian Goodfellow, Jean Pouget-Abadie, Mehdi Mirza, Bing Xu, David Warde-Farley, Sherjil Ozair, Aaron
Courville, and Yoshua Bengio. Generative adversarial nets. InAdvances in neural information processing
systems, pages 2672–2680, 2014.
Don W Gotterbarn, Amy Bruckman, Catherine Flick, Keith Miller, and Marty J Wolf. Acm code of ethics:
a guide for positive action, 2018.
Brian W Head et al. Wicked problems in public policy.Public policy, 3(2):101, 2008.
Yasmeen Hitti, Eunbee Jang, Ines Moreno, and Carolyne Pelletier. Proposed taxonomy for gender bias in
text; a ﬁltering methodology for the gender generalization subtype. InProceedings of the First Workshop
on Gender Bias in Natural Language Processing, pages 8–17, 2019.
Jordan Hoffmann, Louis Maestrati, Yoshihide Sawada, Jian Tang, Jean Michel Sellier, and Yoshua Bengio.
Data-driven approach to encoding and decoding 3-d crystal structures.arXiv preprint arXiv:1909.00949,
2019.
IEEE. Ieee standard review — ethically aligned design: A vision for prioritizing human wellbeing with
artiﬁcial intelligence and autonomous systems. In2017 IEEE Canada International Humanitarian Tech-
nology Conference (IHTC), pages 197–201. IEEE, 2017.
Anna Jobin, Marcello Ienca, and Effy Vayena. Artiﬁcial intelligence: the global landscape of ethics guide-
lines.arXiv preprint arXiv:1906.11668, 2019.
Christopher M Jones and Daniel M Kammen. Quantifying carbon footprint reduction opportunities for us
households and communities.Environmental science &amp; technology, 45(9):4088–4095, 2011.
Lynn H Kaack, George H Chen, and M Granger Morgan. Truck trafﬁc monitoring with satellite images. InProceedings of the Conference on Computing &amp; Sustainable Societies, pages 155–164. ACM, 2019.
Yann LeCun, Léon Bottou, Yoshua Bengio, Patrick Haffner, et al.
Gradient-based learning applied to
document recognition.Proceedings of the IEEE, 86(11):2278–2324, 1998.
Kelly Levin, Benjamin Cashore, Steven Bernstein, and Graeme Auld. Overcoming the tragedy of super
wicked problems: constraining our future selves to ameliorate global climate change.Policy sciences, 45
(2):123–152, 2012.
Nate G McDowell, Nicholas C Coops, Pieter SA Beck, Jeffrey Q Chambers, Chandana Gangodagamage,
Jeffrey A Hicke, Cho-ying Huang, Robert Kennedy, Dan J Krofcheck, Marcy Litvak, et al.
Global
satellite monitoring of climate-induced vegetation disturbances.Trends in plant science, 20(2):114–123,
2015.
Roger Nkambou, Riichiro Mizoguchi, and Jacqueline Bourdeau.Advances in intelligent tutoring systems,
volume 308. Springer Science &amp; Business Media, 2010.
Silvio Nocera, Cayetano Ruiz-Alarcón-Quintero, and Federico Cavallaro. Assessing carbon emissions from
road transport through trafﬁc ﬂow estimators.Transportation Research Part C: Emerging Technologies,
95:125–148, 2018.
Benjamin D Nye. Intelligent tutoring systems by and for the developing world: A review of trends and
approaches for educational technology in a global context.International Journal of Artiﬁcial Intelligence
in Education, 25(2):177–203, 2015.
11I Perisic.
How artiﬁcial intelligence is shaking up the job market.https://www.weforum.org/
agenda/2018/09/artificial-intelligence-shaking-up-job-market/, 2018. Ac-
cessed: 2019-11-25.
Rimma Pivovarov, Adler J Perotte, Edouard Grave, John Angiolillo, Chris H Wiggins, and Noémie Elhadad.
Learning probabilistic phenotypes from heterogeneous ehr data.Journal of biomedical informatics, 58:
156–165, 2015.
Marco Tulio Ribeiro, Sameer Singh, and Carlos Guestrin. Why should i trust you?: Explaining the predic-
tions of any classiﬁer. InProceedings of the 22nd ACM SIGKDD international conference on knowledge
discovery and data mining, pages 1135–1144. ACM, 2016.
David Rolnick, Priya L Donti, Lynn H Kaack, Kelly Kochanski, Alexandre Lacoste, Kris Sankaran, An-
drew Slavin Ross, Nikola Milojevic-Dupont, Natasha Jaques, Anna Waldman-Brown, Alexandra Luc-
cioni, et al. Tackling climate change with machine learning.arXiv preprint arXiv:1906.05433, 2019.
RSS.
A guide for ethical data science.https://www.actuaries.org.uk/system/files/
field/document/An%20Ethical%20Charter%20for%20Date%20Science%20WEB%
20FINAL.PDF., 2019. Accessed: 2019-11-25.
Victor Schmidt, Alexandra Luccioni, S Karthik Mukkavilli, Narmada Balasooriya, Kris Sankaran, Jennifer
Chayes, and Yoshua Bengio. Visualizing the consequences of climate change using cycle-consistent
adversarial networks.arXiv preprint arXiv:1905.03709, 2019.
Lars Wilko Sommer, Tobias Schuchert, and Jürgen Beyerer. Fast deep vehicle detection in aerial images.
In2017 IEEE Winter Conference on Applications of Computer Vision (WACV), pages 311–319. IEEE,
2017.
Patrick Suppes and Mona Morningstar. Computer-assisted instruction.Science, 166(3903):343–350, 1969.
M Szczepánski.
Economic impacts of artiﬁcial intelligence (ai), european parliamentary research ser-
vice, pe 637.967.http://europarl.europa.eu/RegData/etudes/BRIE/2019/637967/
EPRS_BRI(2019)637967_EN.pdf, 2019. Accessed: 2019-11-25.
UNHCR.
The
sustainable
development
goals
and
addressing
statelessness.https://
www.refworld.org/docid/58b6e3364.html, 2017. Accessed: 2019-11-25.
José R Vázquez-Canteli and Zoltán Nagy.
Reinforcement learning for demand response: A review of
algorithms and modeling techniques.Applied energy, 235:1072–1089, 2019.
Stefan Voigt, Thomas Kemper, Torsten Riedlinger, Ralph Kieﬂ, Klaas Scholte, and Harald Mehl. Satellite
image analysis for disaster and crisis-management support.IEEE transactions on geoscience and remote
sensing, 45(6):1520–1528, 2007.
Cyril Voyant, Gilles Notton, Soteris Kalogirou, Marie-Laure Nivet, Christophe Paoli, Fabrice Motte, and
Alexis Fouilloy. Machine learning methods for solar radiation forecasting: A review.Renewable Energy,
105:569–582, 2017.
Sun Wei, Zhang Chongchong, and Sun Cuiping. Carbon pricing prediction based on wavelet transform
and k-elm optimized by bat optimization algorithm in china ets: the case of shanghai and hubei carbon
markets.Carbon Management, 9(6):605–617, 2018.
James Wexler, Mahima Pushkarna, Tolga Bolukbasi, Martin Wattenberg, Fernanda Viégas, and Jimbo Wil-
son. The what-if tool: Interactive probing of machine learning models.IEEE transactions on visualiza-
tion and computer graphics, 26(1):56–65, 2019.
Jenna Wiens, Suchi Saria, Mark Sendak, Marzyeh Ghassemi, Vincent X Liu, Finale Doshi-Velez, Kenneth
Jung, Katherine Heller, David Kale, Mohammed Saeed, et al. Do no harm: a roadmap for responsible
machine learning for health care.Nature medicine, 25(9):1337–1340, 2019.
Rich Zemel, Yu Wu, Kevin Swersky, Toni Pitassi, and Cynthia Dwork. Learning fair representations. InInternational Conference on Machine Learning, pages 325–333, 2013.
12</biblio>
</article>
